Sewall Wright Papers 1895-1988 Mss.Ms.Coll.60
American Philosophical Society
Sewall Wright Papers
1885-1988
Mss.Ms.Coll.60
American Philosophical Society
17.0 Linear feet
Sewall Wright ranks among the most influential figures in the field of population genetics during the 20th century, and made important contributions to biostatistics, biometrics, and evolutionary theory. These papers contain much of Wright's professional correspondence, scattered research notes, and drafts of a small number of papers.
Wright, Sewall, 1889-1988
Bibliography
Provine, William B., Sewall Wright and Evolutionary Biology (Chicago: Univ. of Chicago, 1978). Call no.: B W937p.
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
American Association for the Advancement of Science Correspondence (15 folders) 1921-1970
American Institute of Biological Sciences Records (5 folders) 1950-1963
American Society of Zoologists Records (25 folders) 1933-1950
American Statistical Association Records (15 folders) 1931-1962
Babcock, Ernest Brown Correspondence (3 items) 1924-1946
Beadle, George Wells Correspondence (24 items) 1942-1965
Blakeslee, Albert Francis Correspondence (2 items) 1936-1940
Cain, Arthur James Correspondence (4 items) 1950-1951
Carnegie Institution of Washington Correspondence (7 folders) 1921-1949
Caspari, Ernst Wilhelm Correspondence (3 items) 1947-1965
Castle, William Ernest Correspondence (28 items) 1916-1962
Crow, James F. Correspondence (21 items) 1947-1981
Delbruck, Max Correspondence (10 items) 1942-1945
Demerec, Milislav Correspondence (24 items) 1932-1956
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Correspondence (6 folders) 1937-1974
Dobzhansky, Theodisius -- Genetics of natural populations. XVIII experiments on chromosomes of Drosophila pseudoobscura from different geographic regions Manuscripts (28 pages) 1948
Dubinin, Nikolai Petrovich -- Work of Soviet biologists - Theoretical genetics Manuscripts (4 pages) n.d.
Dunn, Leslie Clarence Correspondence (59 items) 1919-1971
East, Edward Murray Correspondence (4 items) 1932-1936
Emerson, Rollins Adams Correspondence (2 items) 1939
Ephrussi, Boris Correspondence (6 items) 1936-1946
Fisher, Ronald Aylmer Correspondence (10 items) 1931-1950
Genetics Records (24 folders) 1931-1972
Genetics Society of America Records (22 folders) 1931-1950
Glass, Bentley Correspondence (7 items) 1950-1955
Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict Correspondence (7 items) 1922-1951
Goodale, Hubert Dana Correspondence (6 items) 1932-1947
Haldane, John Burdon Sanderson Correspondence (23 items) 1919-1968
Heidenthal, Gertrude Correspondence (29 items) 1934-1958
Hollaender, Alexander Correspondence (31 items) 1948-1960
Lederberg, Joshua Correspondence (3 items) 1954-1973
Lerner, Isadore Michael Correspondence (10 items) 1932-1952
Lewontin, Richard Charles Correspondence (9 items) 1959-1977
Li, Ching Chun Correspondence (28 items) 1944-1977
Little, Clarence Cook Correspondence (28 items) 1918-1956
Luria, Salvador Edward Correspondence (2 items) 1947-1959
Mayr, Ernst Correspondence (7 items) 1944-1951
Muller, Hermann Joseph Correspondence (29 items) 1928-1967
National Academy of Sciences Records (36 folders) 1945-1979
National Research Council Records (21 folders) 1931-1973
National Science Foundation Records (13 folders) 1952-1981
Neel, James V. Correspondence (5 items) 1939-1965
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences Records (18 folders) 1953-1968
Provine, William B. -- Transcripts of oral history interviews Transcripts (2 boxes) 1969-1980
Roscoe B. Jackson Memorial Laboratory Records (7 folders) 1948-1961
Seventh International Congress of Genetics Records (8 items) 1936-1937
Shull, George Harrison Correspondence (2 items) 1922-1934
Simpson, George Gaylord Correspondence (5 items) 1945-1947
Sixth International Congress of Genetics Records (9 folders) 1931-1937
Sonneborn, Tracy M. Correspondence (35 items) 1943-1952
Stadler, Lewis John Correspondence (21 items) 1931-1953
Stalker, Harrison Dailey Correspondence (4 items) 1939-1964
Stern, Curt Correspondence (25 items) 1932-1967
Sturtevant, Alfred Henry Correspondence (11 items) 1934-1948
Timofeeff-Ressovsky, Nikolai W. Correspondence (2 items) 1936-1937
University of Chicago Records (28 folders) 1927-1947
Wallace, Bruce Correspondence (11 items) 1950-1968
Whiting, Phineas W. Correspondence (13 items) 1934-1954
Wilson, Edwin Bidwell Correspondence (11 items) 1938-1954
Wright, Sewall -- Biographical and autobiographical materials Manuscripts (14 folders) 1897-1980
Wright, Sewall -- Research data and notes Manuscripts (2 boxes) 1928-1973
Related Archival Materials note
The APS collections include the papers of a number of Wright's contemporaries in genetics and evolutionary biology, notably Theodosius Dobzhansky (B D65), Herbert Spencer Jennings (B J44), and George Gaylord Simpson (Ms. Coll. 31).
He appears as a correspondent in several other collections, including A. F. Blakeslee (B B585), Charles B. Davenport (B D27), Milan Demerec (B D394), L. C. Dunn (B D917), Hubert Dana Goodale (B G61), Michael Lerner (B L563), C.C. Li (Ms. Coll. 127), Jack Schultz (Ms. Coll. 27), Curt Stern (Ms. Coll. 5), and Ann Roe (B R621).
Separated Materials note
Tape recordings of oral history interviews conducted by William Provine have been transferred to the APS recordings collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Wright Papers were initially collected and organized by William Provine for his book, Sewall Wright and Evolutionary Biology (University of Chicago, 1978), and donated by him to the APS Library in 1988.
Provine had arranged Wright's papers largely by subject, however at the APS the correspondence has been reorganized by correspondent. Records of Provine's arrangement are available.
Scope and Contents note
The Sewall Wright Papers document the thought and professional activities of one of the 20th century's greatest quantitative evolutionary biologists. Containing Wright's professional correspondence, scattered research notes, and drafts of a small number of papers
Series I. Correspondence, 1931-1991 27 boxes, 13.5 linear feet
Series II. Manuscripts 2 boxes, 1 linear foot
Series IIa. Research data and notes 2 boxes, 1 linear foot
Series III. Biographical and autobiographical material 0.5 boxes, 0.25 linear feet
Series IIIa. Transcripts of oral history interviews 1.5 boxes, 0.75 linear feet
Series IV. Photographs 1 box, 0.5 linear feet
As photgraphs from the collection are digitized, links to the digital versions of images are included in the inventory. You may also view a gallery of all images here.
Biographical/Historical note
One of the pioneers of quantitative genetics and evolutionary biology, Sewall Wright was born in Melrose, Massachusetts, to Philip Green Wright and Elizabeth Quincy Sewall Wright on December 21, 1889. He was, as he was fond of noting, the child of two cousins - the result of inbreeding. From early in his career, Wright contributed to emerging understandings of Darwinian natural selection and Mendelian genetics to lay the groundwork for modern population genetics and the Neo-Darwinian "modern synthesis." He made profound theoretical contributions in the theories of genetic drift and shifting balance, and was equally important in analyzing problems in the relationship of genotype and phenotype, biometrics, and biostatistics.
The hallmark of Wright's scientific work was his ability to combine experimental and theoretical approaches, and to apply novel mathematical and statistical methods to analyze problems in biology. Many of his theoretical insights took years to prove empirically, and others were so computationally intensive that they could not easily be tackled in the pre-computer era, but his influence, along with that of his friend, J.B.S. Haldane, and some-time antagonist, R. A. Fisher, helped reorient the disciplines of evolutionary biology and genetics along more rigorous, quantitive lines.
Wright's professional education began at Lombard College (BS, 1911), now defunct, and the University of Illinois (MS, 1912), from which he gained admission to Harvard. Opting to work on guinea pigs, one of the first groups of animals to be thoroughly studied by geneticists, Wright received his doctorate of science in 1915 for the lucidly-titled dissertation, An Intensive Study of the Inheritance of Color and of Other Coat Characteristics in Guinea Pigs. His choice of topic proved particularly fruitful in landing his first professional position, as Senior Animal Husbandman with the U.S. Department of Agriculture.
The U.S.D.A. was interested in having the brilliant young geneticist begin to analyze the extensive set of trait records they had gathered for their inbred guinea pig colonies established in 1906, all in the hope of applying the findings to improve livestock breeding. To make the connections between guinea pigs and swine, Wright felt it necessary first to develop a general theory of population genetics, which in turn, he argued, required more powerful and flexible statistical techniques than had previously been used. By 1918, Wright had worked out a new statistical approach, path analysis, which now has wide application in sociology, econometrics, and behavioral genetics, and with this new tool, began investigating some fundamental questions in inheritance and population genetics, delving into the relative influence of heredity and the environment in determining the appearance of traits.
By the early 1920s, Wright's methodological and theoretical approaches had matured, and he later believed that by the time he left the U.S.D.A. for the University of Chicago in 1926, he had developed most of his fundamental ideas about evolutionary processes. His first theoretical paper, the influential "Evolution in Mendelian populations," was written in 1925, though not published until 1931. Among the most controversial and far-reaching of his ideas was the theory of genetic drift, which was as widely misunderstood and misrepresented, according to Wright, as it was widely known, and which was the crux of a long-standing argument in the literature with R.A. Fisher, among others. Based on his findings, Wright suggested that small, random genetic changes ("drift") in small local populations can greatly increase the "field of variability" available for natural selection. The implications for understanding the speciation process and the rates and trajectories of evolutionary change were profound, and although controversial, his theory had a galvanizing influence on evolutionary studies, expanding the range of potential evolutionary mechanisms and invigorating debate over evolutionary mechanics. Although Wright is often said to have presented a "non-Darwinian" model for evolutionary change, he later insisted that what he had provided was instead a means of producing variability upon which the powerful forces of Darwinian natural selection could operate.
At the U.S.D.A. and at the University of Chicago, Wright also began to develop a view of evolution as consisting largely of "occasional shifts" from one state of genetic near equilibrium to another, rather than the progressivist paradigm that had dominated evolutionary studies (maintaining that evolution proceeded by the slow, incremental accumulation of small mutations and concentrating on the fixation of discrete characters). Perhaps more subtly, Wright also insisted upon focussing upon the evolution of "interaction systems" as opposed to isolated traits or organisms in isolation of their populations, laying the groundwork for understanding the evolutionary process as occurring at more than one hierarchically related levels. "An organism," he wrote, "is not a mere aggregation of characters, but a harmonious, tightly integrated entity," implying that this integration was as true at the level of the population as the gene. It would not be overstatement to suggest that Wright's theoretical, statistical, and empirical studies, in interaction with the work of Fisher, Haldane, George Gaylord Simpson, and others, were instrumental in fashioning the Neo-Darwinian synthesis of the 1940s, representing the firm fusion of Mendelian and Darwinian principles, and in galvanizing the macroevolutionary studies of the 1970s and 1980s.
At Chicago, Wright was employed (successively) as Associate Professor of Zoology, Professor, and the Ernest D. Burton Distinguished Service Professor, earning a reputation as a conscientious, demanding, and engaging teacher, who always incorporated the latest available information in his lectures. He also spent visiting years as Hitchcock Professor at the University of California Berkeley (1943) and as Fulbright Professor at the University of Edinburgh (1949-1950).
In 1955, Wright joined the faculty of the University of Wisconsin as Leon J. Cole Professor of Genetics, and worked for five years until his "retirement" in 1960. For Wright, though, retirement did not mean a slacking off of research. Virtually until the day of his death at age 98, Wright remained an active participant in the Genetics Department at Wisconsin as Professor Emeritus. Many of the 210 scientific papers he wrote during his career were published after his departure from Chicago -- literally up until the time of his death -- and his magnum opus, the four volume Evolution and the Genetics of Populations (Chicago, 1968-1978), was completed only months before his 90th birthday.
Wright's professional associations were numerous, as were the laurels of his innovative and influential scientific career. He was awarded ten honorary doctorates during his lifetime, was president of five scientific organizations and the recipient of nine medals or prizes, and he held memberships in thirteen scientific societies or national and international organizations. In 1932, he was elected to membership in the American Philosophical Society.
Wright married Louise Lane Williams in 1921, with whom he had three children, Richard, Robert, and Elizabeth Quincy Wright Rose. Louise Wright died in 1975, followed by Sewall on March 3, 1988, in Madison.
House Un-American Activities Committee; National Academy of Sciences. (U.S.); National Research Council (U.S.); Provine, William; University of Chicago.; Evolution (Biology); Genetic algebras; Genetics; Population genetics
- Series I. Correspondence, 1895-1988; 13.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Incoming and outgoing professional correspondence, with a lesser quantity of administrative and personal correspondence.
  The bulk of Wright's professional correspondence concerns discussions, elaborations, or clarifications of his ideas with respect to those of other scientists, or commentary on papers submitted for publication. Wright frequently served as a referee or commentator for professional journals. Among the more interesting correspondence are letters concerned with the social implications of genetic theories and discussions of the relationship of science and politics.
  Correspondence relating to Wright's administrative responsibilities date mostly from his years at the University of Chicago, or relate to his work with professional socities. The majority consists of recommendations, elections, candidates for positions or offices, and the definition of institutional goals and agendas. There is also some correspondence relating to honors and awards received by Wright.
  Finally, a relatively small number of items are concerned with Wright's philosophical views.
  In general, correspondence is filed alphabetically by author, then chronologically by date written. In instances in which letters were written on behalf of an institution, they are filed under the name of the institution rather than the author, per se.
  - Abbott, Clyde P., 1925 (Box Series I-1)
  - Abbott, W.S., 1924-1926 (Box Series I-1)
  - Abrams, Gordon C., 1956-1957 (Box Series I-1)
  - Abstracts in Anthropology, 1970 (Box Series I-1)
    Smith, M. Estelle
  - Academic Press, Inc., 1966 (Box Series I-1)
    Iacono, Anthony
  - Adair, Fred L., n. d. (Box Series I-1)
  - Adams, Elliot Q., 1945 (Box Series I-1)
  - Adams, James Ring, n. d. (Box Series I-1)
  - Adelmann, H, B., 1936 (Box Series I-1)
  - Adler, Julius, 1966 (Box Series I-1)
  - Advances in Genetics, 1945 (Box Series I-1)
    Demerec, M.
  - Adkisson, V.W., 1952 (Box Series I-1)
  - Aebischer, M., 1934 (Box Series I-1)
  - Aeurbach, C., 1970 (Box Series I-1)
  - Alderfer, William K., 1962 (Box Series I-1)
  - Aldrich, W.W., 1917 (Box Series I-1)
  - Alexander, Brooke, 1961 (Box Series I-1)
  - Alexander, Howard W., 1945 (Box Series I-1)
  - Alexander, Jerome, 1941-1949 (Box Series I-1)
  - Allard, R.W., 1965-1971 (Box Series I-1)
  - Allee, W.C., 1927-1954 (Box Series I-1)
    Clyde
  - Allen, Garland E., 1979 (Box Series I-1)
  - Allen, Glover M., 1968 (Box Series I-1)
  - Allen, Gordon, 1954 (Box Series I-1)
  - Allen, Sally Lyman, 1954-55 (Box Series I-1)
  - Alvarez, Walter C., 1969 (Box Series I-1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1953-77 (Box Series I-1)
    Burhoe, Ralph W.; Davis, Saville
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1921-1970; 15 folders (Box Series I-1)
    American Association for the Advancement of Science; Cole, Leon Jacob; Committee activities; Conferences and symposia; Congratulations, greetings, thanks -- 50-year membership; Genetics of plants; Population genetics; Publication -- Science; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1949 (Box Series I-1)
    - Bevan, William, 1970 (Box Series I-1)
    - Cole, Leon, 1921 (Box Series I-1)
    - Du Shane, Graham, 1962 (Box Series I-1)
    - Irwin, M. R., 1947 (Box Series I-1)
    - La Rue, George, 1934 (Box Series I-1)
    - Mayer, Joseph, 1956 (Box Series I-1)
    - Metz, C.W., 1947 (Box Series I-1)
    - Meyerhoff, Howard, 1951 (Box Series I-1)
    - Moulton, F.R., 1944 (Box Series I-1)
    - Oppenheimer, Jane M., 1955 (Box Series I-1)
    - Ullman, Morris B., 1962 (Box Series I-1)
    - Valentine, Willard L., 1966 (Box Series I-1)
    - Ward, Henry B., 1933 (Box Series I-1)
    - Wolfe, Dael, 1961 (Box Series I-1)
  - The American Biology Teacher, 1941 (Box Series I-1)
    Colin, E.C.
  - American Cancer Society, 1949 (Box Series I-1)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1955 (Box Series I-1)
    Dictionary of American Biography; James, Edward T.
  - American Dental Association, 1960 (Box Series I-1)
    Pearlman, Sholom
  - American Eugenics Society, 1957 (Box Series I-1)
  - American Genetic Society (Box Series I-1)
    - American Genetic Society, 1954 (Box Series I-1)
    - Bamford, Ronald, 1950 (Box Series I-1)
    - Cook, Robert, 1932-51 (Box Series I-1)
    - Lake, B, C., 1956-64 (Box Series I-1)
  - American Institute of Biological Sciences, 1950-1963; 5 folders (Box Series I-1)
    American Institute of Biological Sciences; Committee activities; Conferences and symposia; Publication
    - Albritton, Errett C., 1950-1952 (Box Series I-1)
    - Freemont-Smith, F., 1961-1963 (Box Series I-1)
    - Hylander, Clarence J., 1952 (Box Series I-1)
    - Meyer, Samuel L., 1952-1953 (Box Series I-1)
    - Shilling, Charles W., 1961 (Box Series I-1)
  - American International Publishers, 1922 (Box Series I-1)
    Rommel, George M.
  - American Journal of Medical Genetics-Opitz, 1978 (Box Series I-1)
    Opitz, John M.
  - The American Journal of Human Genetics--Steinberg, 1958-60 (Box Series I-1)
    Steinberg, Arthur G.
  - The American Journal of Sociology-Blumer, 1944 (Box Series I-1)
    Blumer, Herbert
  - American Medical Association, 1955 (Box Series I-1)
    Freyder, Maydalene
  - American Mouse Club, 1931 (Box Series I-1)
    Gates, William H.
  - The American Naturalist (Box Series I-1)
    - Baker, W.K., 1968 (Box Series I-1)
    - Bryson, Vernon, 1963 (Box Series I-1)
    - Cattell, J. McKeen (Jacques), 1931-55 (Box Series I-1)
    - Dunn, L.C., 1950-55 (Box Series I-1)
    - La Duke, Frances, 1968 (Box Series I-1)
    - Lewontin, R.C., 1969 (Box Series I-1)
    - Sokal, Robert R., 1970-74 (Box Series I-1)
    - Taylor, Randolph Wm., 1944 (Box Series I-1)
    - Wallace, Bruce, 1967 (Box Series I-1)
    - Williams, George C., n.d. (Box Series I-1)
  - American Philosophical Society (Box Series I-1)
    - Bell, W.J., Jr.; Shryock, R. H., 1967 (Box Series I-1)
    - Bronk, Detlev W., 1939 (Box Series I-1)
    - Corner, George W., 1962-71 (Box Series I-1)
    - Eisenhart, L. P., 1949-51 (Box Series I-1)
    - Goodspeed, Arthur W.; Miller, John A., 1932-33 (Box Series I-1)
    - McClung, C. E., 1933 (Box Series I-1)
    - Moe, Henry Allen, 1961 (Box Series I-1)
  - American Scandinavian Society, 1922 (Box Series I-1)
    Creese, James
  - American Scientist, 1962 (Box Series I-1)
    Gillispie, Mrs. Charles C.
  - American Society of Animal Production (Box Series I-1)
    - Briggs, H. M., 1949 (Box Series I-1)
    - Cole. L. J., 1933 (Box Series I-1)
    - Craft, W. A., 1931 (Box Series I-1)
    - Hill, J.A., 1932 (Box Series I-1)
    - Hogan, A.G., 1933 (Box Series I-1)
    - Loeffel, J., 1933 (Box Series I-1)
    - Whiting, P.W., 1934 (Box Series I-1)
    - Proceedings, 1931 (Box Series I-1)
  - American Society of Human Genetics (Box Series I-2)
    - Brown, Judith A.; Bloom, Arthur, 1980 (Box Series I-2)
    - Dewey, William J., 1961 (Box Series I-2)
    - Gardner, Eldon J., 1956 (Box Series I-2)
    - Herndon, C. Nash, 1956 (Box Series I-2)
    - Murphy, Edmund A., 1976 (Box Series I-2)
  - American Society of Naturalists (Box Series I-2)
    - American Society of Naturalists, 1950 (Box Series I-2)
    - Cole, L. J., 1931 (Box Series I-2)
    - Demerec, M., 1933-1934 (Box Series I-2)
    - Glass, Bentley, 1951-1952 (Box Series I-2)
    - Hargitt, George T., 1933 (Box Series I-2)
    - Lillie, Frank R., 1933 (Box Series I-2)
    - Lindstrom, E. W., 1933 (Box Series I-2)
    - Mangelsdorf, Paul C., 1951-1952 (Box Series I-2)
    - Muller, H. J., 1944 (Box Series I-2)
    - Plough, Harold H., 1953 (Box Series I-2)
    - Rhoades, M. M.; Van Niel, Cornelius, 1951 (Box Series I-2)
    - Stone, Wilson S.; Weiss, Paul Alfred, 1948 (Box Series I-2)
  - American Society of Zoology, 1933-1950; 25 folders (Box Series I-2)
    Business; Committee activities; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs -- American Society of Zoologists; Zoology
    - [American Society of Zoology], [1944-50] (Box Series I-2)
    - Adams, A. Elizabeth, 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Adelman, H.B., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Allee, W. C., 1944 (Box Series I-2)
    - Brown, F. A., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Coker, R. F., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Danforth, C.H., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Demerec, M., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Domm, L. V., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Executive Committee, 1945 (Box Series I-2)
    - Figge, F.H.J., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Goodrich, H.B., 1935 (Box Series I-2)
    - Hamburger, Viktor, 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Hartmann, C. G., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Hess, W. N.; Executive Committee, 1947-49 (Box Series I-2)
    - Hisaw, F.L., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Kempton, R.T., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Kornhauser, 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Lillie, F.R., 1944 (Box Series I-2)
    - Minich, D.E., 1946 (Box Series I-2)
    - Nelson, Thurlow G., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Noland, L.E., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Parker, G.H., 1933 (Box Series I-2)
    - Pollister, A. V., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Twitty, V.C., 1947 (Box Series I-2)
    - Zeleny, Charles, 1933 (Box Series I-2)
  - American Statistical Association, 1931-1962; 15 folders (Box Series I-2)
    Business; Conferences and symposia; Editorial matters; Genetics; Publication; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs; Statistics, biostatistics, biometrics
    - American Statistical Association, n. d (Box Series I-2)
    - Berkson, Joseph, 1936 (Box Series I-2)
    - Bliss, C. I., 1942 (Box Series I-2)